<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be inquired of within the diocesse of Peterborough in the visitation of the reuerend father in God, Thomas, by the permission of God, Lord Bishop of Peterborough this present yeare 1605 and presentment to be made thereof by the churchwardens and side-men for that purpose lawfully appointed, in visitations, synods, or elswhere, within the dioces aforesaid, at any other time, when occasion shall be offered, giuing in an answer to euery particular article.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Peterborough. Bishop (1600-1630 : Dove)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10314.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2646</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24448875</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24448875</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00240)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1851:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be inquired of within the diocesse of Peterborough in the visitation of the reuerend father in God, Thomas, by the permission of God, Lord Bishop of Peterborough this present yeare 1605 and presentment to be made thereof by the churchwardens and side-men for that purpose lawfully appointed, in visitations, synods, or elswhere, within the dioces aforesaid, at any other time, when occasion shall be offered, giuing in an answer to euery particular article.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Peterborough. Bishop (1600-1630 : Dove)</author>
                  <author>Dove, Thomas, 1555-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legat, printer to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B².</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27674:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27674:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Articles TO BE INQVIRED OF <hi>within the Dioceſſe of Peterborough in the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of the Reuerend father in God, <hi>THOMAS,</hi> by the permiſſion <hi>of God, Lord Biſhop of Peterborough this preſent yeare</hi> 1605. <hi>And preſentment to</hi> be made thereof by the Churchwardens and Side-men for that purpoſe <hi>lawfully appointed, in viſitations, Synods, or elswhere, within the Dioces</hi> aforeſaid, at any other time, when occaſion ſhall be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>giuing in an anſwer to euery particular</hi> Article.</p>
            <p>Printed by IOHN LEGAT, Printer to the Vniuerſitie of Cambridge. 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:27674:2"/>
            <head>The tenour of the Oth to be miniſtred.</head>
            <p>YOu ſhall ſweare, that all fauour, hatred, malice, hope of reward, or gaine, feare of diſpleaſure, and all other vnlawfull affections ſet aſide, you ſhall vpon due conſideration of theſe Articles giuen you in charge, preſent euery ſuch perſon of or within your pariſh, as hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted or made any offence or fault mentioned in any of theſe Articles, or which are vehemently ſuſpected or defamed of any ſuch offence or fault, wherein you ſhall deale vprightly, neither of malice preſenting any contrarie to truth, nor corruptly ſparing to preſent any, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the truth, hauing in this action God before your eyes, with an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt zeale to maintaine truth, and to ſuppreſſe vice, So helpe you God in Ieſus Chriſt, and by the contents of this booke.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:27674:2"/>
            <head>ARTICLES TO BE INQVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>of within the Dioceſſe of Peter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough.</hi> Ann. Dom. 1605.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N primis, whether is there any in your pariſh, that hath affirmed that the forme of Gods worſhippe in the Church of England eſtabliſhed by law, and contained in the booke of Common praier, and adminiſtration of Sacraments, is a corrupt, ſuperſtitious, or vnlawfull worſhip of God, or containeth any thing in it that is repugnant to the Scriptures: or any that hath affirmed, that any of the nine and thirtie Articles agreed vpon by the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Biſhops of both Provinces, and the whole Cleargie in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation holden in London, in the yeare of our Lord 1562. for the auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of diuerſities of opinions, and for the eſtabliſhing of conſent tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching true religion, are in any part ſuperſtitious or erronious: Or any that hath affirmed that the rites and ceremonies of the Church of England, by law eſtabliſhed, are wicked, Antichriſtian, or ſuperſtitious. And if you how or haue heard ſay of any ſuch within your pariſh, you are to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi> whether there be any in your pariſh that hath not celebrated and kept the Lords day, commonly called Sunday, and other holy daies, according to Gods holy will and pleaſure and the orders of the Church of England preſcribed in that behalfe. And if there be any ſuch, you ſhall preſent them. Alſo, whether the Common praier hath beene ſaid or ſung in your pariſh church by your Miniſter diſtinctly and reuerently vpon ſuch daies as are appointed to be kept holy by the booke of Common praier, and their Eues, and at conuenient and vſuall times of thoſe daies, and in ſuch conuenient place of your church, ſo as the people may be moſt edified: And whether your Miniſter hath obſerued the orders, rites, and ceremonies preſcribed in the booke of Common praier, as well in reading the holy ſcriptures, and ſaying of praiers, as in the adminiſtration of the ſacraments, without either diminiſhing in regard of preaching, or in any other reſpect, or adding any thing in the matter or forme thereof: And whether the Letanie hath been ſaid or ſung when, and as it ſet downe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27674:3"/>the booke of Common praier, by your parſon, vicar, or curate, in ſome conuenient place of your Church; And alſo vpon wedenſdaies and fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies weekely, though there be no holy daies, at the accuſtomed houres of ſeruice.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Item,</hi> whether is there any within your pariſh that hath couered his head in your church or chappell, in the time of diuine ſeruice, except he haue ſome infirmitie: And whether all manner of perſons in the time of diuine ſeruice haue reuerently knceled vpon their knees, when the generall confeſſion, Letanie, and other praiers are read, and ſtood vp at the ſaying of the Beleefe, according to the booke of common praier. And likewiſe, when in time of diuine ſeruice, the Lord Ieſus hath beene mentioned, due and lowly reuerence hath beene done, by all perſons preſent. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the time of diuine ſeruice, any haue buſied themſelues in the Church, either in talking, or walking, or any other way, then in quiet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance to heare, marke, and vnderſtand that which hath been read, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, or miniſtred, not departing out of the church during the time of ſeruice and ſermon, without ſome vrgent cauſe. And when any idle perſons haue in the churchyard or church porch during the time of diuine ſeruice and preaching, whether the Churchwardens or Queſtmen haue not then cauſed them either to come into the church, or to depart.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Item,</hi> whether againſt the time of euery Communion within your pariſh, there be prouided by the Churchwardens a ſufficient quantitie of fine white bread, and of good and wholeſome wine for the number of the Communicants, and not of beare or ale, or beare or ale and wine together. And whether your parſon, vicar, or Curate, hath adminiſtred the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion ſo often and at ſuch times, as euery pariſhioner may communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate at the leaſt thrice euery yeare, (whereof the feaſt of Eaſter to be one.) And whether euery perſon within your pariſh, beeing of ſufficient age, hath ſo communicated; And whether your Miniſter doth deliuer both the bread and the wine to euery communicant ſeuerally; And whether your parſon, vicar, or curate hath giuen warning to his pariſhioners publikely in the church at morning praier the Sunday before euery time of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of that holy ſacrament, that ſo they might the better prepare themſelues. And if you know any defect to haue beene in any of theſe, you are to preſent it.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your Miniſter haue admitted to the receiuing of the holy communion, any of his cure, which be openly knowne to liue in ſinne notorious without repentance, or any who haue malitiouſly and openly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27674:3"/>contended with their neighbours, vntill they haue beene reconciled: or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other that are common and notorious deprauers of the booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon praier, and adminiſtration of the ſacraments, and of the other rites and ceremonies therein preſcribed: or of any thing that is contained in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Articles agreed vpon in the Conuocation 1562, or of any thing contained in the booke of ordering Prieſts and Biſhops, or to any that haue ſpoken againſt and depraued his Maieſties ſoueraigne authoritie in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall. And whether, when he hath celebrated the holy Communion, he hath admitted any to the ſame but ſuch as doe kneele, did ſuch as come to publike praier according to the orders of the church of England.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your Parſon, vicar, or curate ſaying the publike praiers, or miniſtring the ſacraments, or other rites of the church, hath worne a decent and comely ſurpliſſe with ſleeues, and his hood, if he be a graduate agreeable to the orders of the Vniuerſitie: And whether in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing of the ſacrament of Baptiſme, he hath vſed the ſigne of the croſſe, according as it is preſcribed by the booke of common praier, not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing any man to anſwer as godfather for his owne child, nor any godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her or godmother to make any other anſwer or ſpeech then by the book of Common praier is preſcribed in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your Miniſter, beeing a licenſed preacher, and reſident upon his liuing, hath preached euery Sunday: and if he be not a preacher, whether hath he procured ſermons to be preached in his cure once in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moneth at the leaſt, by preachers lawfully licenſed: and in defect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whether hath he read a Homelie preſcribed by authoritie to the intents aforeſaid. And if he be not reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpon his benefice, whether is his charge ſupplied by a Curate that is a ſufficient and licenſed preacher. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe they in their Sermons pray for the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, giuing his Maieſtie his vſuall title and ſtyle, for our gratious Queene Anne, the noble prince Henrie, and the reſt of the King and Queenes royall iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, according to the order preſcribed in the late Canons, exhorting alſo the people to obedience to his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, doth euery Sunday and holiday, halfe an houre at the leaſt, before euening praier, call for, heare, and inſtruct all the children, apprentiſes, and ſeruants of both ſexes, that be of conuenient age, in the Lords praier, the ten Commandements, and in the Articles of beleefe, and diligently examine them, teaching them the Carachiſme ſet forth by authoritie. And whether for that purpoſe he doth
<pb facs="tcp:27674:4"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:27674:4"/>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:27674:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:27674:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:27674:6"/>take the names of them all, and by courſe call certaine of them by name, euery Sonday and holiday to come to learne the ſame Catechiſme. And whether the Churchwardens and ſworne-men doe aſſiſt the Miniſter, as he doth preſcribe them in that godly examination.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your Parſon, vicar, or curate haue married any perſons within your pariſh, without the publiſhing of banes according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church of England, or without lawfull licenſe thereunto ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, or any within the degrees forbidden: or whether there be any in your pariſh that hauing bind diuorced, doe inhabit and keepe companie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and beeing married that haue left their wiues, any man that hath two wiues, any woman that hath two husbands, any that deferre the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnization of matrimonie beeing lawfully contracted, any that haue contracted themſelues without conſent of parents, any that haue beene married in any priuate houſe or chamber, or at any vnlawfull time, but onely betweene the houres of eight and twelue of the clocke in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, who married them, who were the parties ſo married, &amp; who were preſent, at the marriage, expreſſing their names and ſurnames.</p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your Miniſter doth euery Sunday at the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion booke, declare to the people whether there be any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidaies or faſting daies the weeke following. And whether doth he ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely denounce Recuſants and excommunicate perſons in the church, that ſo others may be admoniſhed thereby to refraine their companie and ſocietic. And whether doth he viſit the ſicke and inſtruct them and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their diſtreſſe, according to the order of the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> booke, if he be no preacher. And whether doth he refuſe or delay to chriſten any child according to the forme of the booke of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon praier, that is brought to him to the church vpon Sundaies or holidaies to be chriſtened: or to burie any corps that is brought to the church or churchyard, in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme as is preſcribed in the ſaid booke of common praier. And if he haue beene defectiue in any of theſe you muſt preſent him.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Item,</hi> whether you haue a Regiſter booke in parchment to write in all chriſtenings, weddings, and burialls: and whether thoſe chriſtenings, weddings, and burialls, be diligently noted therein: and whether your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter euery Sabboth day after morning or euening praier doth diſtinctly read in the church, the names of all ſuch as haue beene the weeke before either baptized, married, or buried. And whether the Miniſter and church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens doe ſet their hands to euery leaſe of this booke. And whether you haue a cheſt with three lockes wherein the ſaid booke is ſafely kept,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27674:6"/>the Miniſter keeping one key, and each of the Churchwardens another. And whether you haue a ſtrong cheſt for the poore, with three locks, and three keies to the ſame. And whether your Miniſter doth mooue and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort the people to beſtow their almes and charitable deuotion vpon their poore neighbours.</p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your Miniſter doth preach, or adminiſter the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in priuate houſes, or appoint publike and priuate faſts or prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, or hold any priuate conuenticles: And whether doth he were ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent apparrell as is inioyned him by authoritie: And whether he be not a reſorter to Tauernes, or alehouſes, or giueth himſelfe to baſe and ſcruile la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or to drinking or riot, ſpending his time idlely by day or by night, playing at dice, cardes, tables, or any other vnlawfull games: a common hawker, a hunter, ſwearer, or doe giue any euill example of life, whereby the word of God and the religion now receiued may be euill ſpoken of.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, hat bought their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, or come by them by fraud, guile, deceit, or ſimonie: and whether he hath moe benefices then he ought to haue, not hauing ſufficient diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation thereto. And whether doth your Miniſter receiue into his church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excommunicate perſon before he bring to him a true certificate of his abſolution and reſtoring to the church: And whether he hath receiued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny woman deliuered of child begot in fornication to her thankſgiuing in the church, before ſhee hath publikely reconciled her ſelfe in ſuch order as by the officer in that behalfe hath beene to her preſcribed.</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>Item,</hi> what Schoolemaſters haue you within your pariſh, that teach either openly or priuatly, in any ſchoole, gentlemans houſe, or els where, and whether be they of good and ſincer religion: and licenſed by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of this Dioces, or Ordinarie, vnder his hand and ſeale: and whether be they diligent in teaching and bringing vp youth, and to inſtruct them in godlines and vertue: and whether they teach any thing contrarie to the religion now godlily eſtabliſhed, or doe not cauſe their children to reſide vnto the church, to heare diuine ſeruice.</p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>Item,</hi> whether haue you in your church or chappell, the booke of Common praier, lately explained in ſome few points by his Maieſties au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, according to the lawes and his Highneſſe prerogatiue in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, the Bible of the largeſt volume, and other bookes allowed by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. Whether haue you alſo a font of ſtone where baptiſme is to be miniſtred, ſtanding in the auntient vſuall place: in which onely the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhall baptize publikely: a decent communion table in time of diuine
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27674:7"/>ſeruice, with a carpet of ſilke, or other decent ſtuffe: a comely and decent pulpit, ſtanding in a conuenient place.</p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your pariſh Church, chappell, or chancell be well and ſufficiently repaired, and ſo from time to time kept and maintained, the windowes well cloſed, the flores paued plaine and euen, and all things therein orderly and in decent ſort without duſt, or any thing that may be either noiſome or vnſeemely, as beſt becommeth the houſe of God: your churchyards well and ſufficiently repaired, fenced, and maintained with walls, railes, or pales. And whether all perſons excommunicate, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, be kept out of your church. And whether you haue not had plaies, feaſts, banquets, ſuppers, churchales, drinkings, comporall courts or lectes, laynaries, muſters, or any other prophane vſage in your church, chappell, or churchyard: and if there be any ſuch abuſes you ſhall preſent the ſame.</p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your Churchwardens haue yearely giuen an account of the church goods committed to their charge, and of other receipts and expenſes: and whether they haue ſold any bells, lead, or other church goods, without the conſent of the Ordinarie firſt had in writing: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue imploied all ſuch goods, receipts, and ſummes of money to the vſe of the church: and whether the Churchwardens and ſworne-men in former times haue of any priuate corrupt affection concealed any crime or diſorder done in their times, and haue not preſemed the ſame: and what be the names of ſuch Churchwardens, and of ſuch offenders.</p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>Item,</hi> whether you know or haue heard by common ſame of any that liue vitiouſly in fornication, adulterie, inceſt, drunkennes, or vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, common ſwearers, prophaners of the Sabboth, vſurers, bawdes, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balds, harbourers, maintainers, or receiuers of any ſuch leud perſons, or any which carrie, ſend away, or conuey ſuch perſons before they be puniſhed, or vehemently ſuſpected of any ſuch faults: any woman which hath beene begotten with child or liued incontinently before ſhee was married, who hath not yet ſatisfied the congregation, or of any which ſight, chide, or brawle in church or churchyard. And what be their names.</p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>Item,</hi> whether the Miniſter and clarke, and the Churchwardens, with certaine of the ſubſtantiall men of the pariſh in Rogation weeke, walke about their pariſh: and whether at their returne to the Church, they make their common praiers. Alſo who they be that doe negligently or wilfully abſent themſelues from praiers on Sondaies and holidaies, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuerently behaue themſelues in the church the time of divine ſeruice.</p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Item,</hi> whether there be any in your pariſh that doe adminiſter vpon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27674:7"/>goods of thoſe that be dead without lawfull authoritie, or any that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, chaunge, forge, or hinder the performance of the Teſtaments or laſt will of the dead, or any executours that hath not fulfilled the Teſtatours will, eſpecially ſuch as haue not diſcharged ſuch legacies as were bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed to the church, or to orphanes, or to high waies, or to ſuch, godly vſes, and what be their names.</p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>Item,</hi> whether doe any Phyſitians, or Chirurgions practiſe phyſicke or chirurgerie within your pariſh that is not thereunto licenſed by the Lord Biſhop of the Dioces.</p>
            <p n="22">22 <hi>Item,</hi> whether the Church of your pariſh be vacant or no, who is the patron thereof, how long it hath beene void, and who doth receiue the tythes, oblations, and other commodities, during the time of the vacation, and by what authoritie.</p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Item,</hi> whether there be any in your pariſh that be ſuſpected to be reconciled to the Pope of Rome his religion, any maſſing Prieſts, Ieſuits, Seminaries, or other which haue receiued authoritie from the Romiſh church: any Papiſts or Recuſants, or any that goe about to depraue the Religion now eſtabliſhed, and that maintaine hereſie, vſe inchantments, witchcrafts, ſorceries, or ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="24">24 <hi>Item,</hi> whether haue you the Canons and Conſtitutions lately ſet forth by authoritie, and for the better obſeruation of them, whether hath your Miniſter read them in your pariſh church or chappell vpon ſome Sondaies and holidaies, according as it is commanded.</p>
            <p n="25">25 <hi>Item,</hi> whether doe you know or haue heard by common fame of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other crime worthie preſentment, the reformation whereof belongeth to the Eccleſiaſticall court: and if you doe, you ſhall as well preſent them which now come to your memorie, as thoſe which ſhall hereafter come to your knowledge, twice by the yeare, according to the Canons lately ſet forth by authoritie, that is to ſay, from henceforth at the feaſt of S. Iohn Baptiſt, commonly called Midſommer, and at the feaſt of the Natiuitie of our Lord, commonly called Chriſtmas.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
